{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Nearly 2,000 people died when the Sultana exploded in this river, but John Wilkes Booth died the day before, so the tragedy received shockingly little press coverage. Monks Mound was built on the eastern banks of this river, which names a civilization that built the city of Cahokia. A control structure was built to reduce its flow into the Atchafalaya River. For ten points, name this American river whose source was identified in 1832 as Minnesota’s Lake Itasca, from which it flows to the Gulf of Mexico.",
      "answer": "Mississippi River"
    },
    {
      "question": "One performer of this instrument wrote the Hohenfriedberger March to celebrate victory in the Second Silesian War. This is the first instrument to play the melody in Ravel’s Bolero, and a solo near the low end of its range opens Debussy’s Prelude to the Afternoon of a Faun. A treatise on playing this instrument was written by Johann Quantz, who taught Frederick the Great. For ten points, name this transverse woodwind instrument whose higher-pitched relatives include the fife and piccolo.",
      "answer": "flute"
    },
    {
      "question": "The success of this work led to a plagiarization lawsuit from Harold Courlander. Sequels to this work include “The Gift” and “The Next Generations.” Tom Moore teaches the intricacies of cockfighting in this series, in which Jemmy deserts the Confederate Army. It ends with Chicken George tracing his lineage from Africa to Tennessee. ABC aired this series, an adaptation of a “Saga of an American Family,” in 1977. For ten points, name this novel and TV miniseries about Kunta Kinte, inspired by the ancestors of author Alex Haley.",
      "answer": "Roots"
    },
    {
      "question": "A commando raid on Kwale killed 11 Italians working in this industry and also captured 14 more workers. The Kaiama Declaration demanded the withdrawal of this industry from land held by the Ijaw people. For his efforts to protect the Ogoni people from human rights violations from companies extracting this resource, Ken Saro-Wiwa was executed in 1995 by the government of Sani Abacha in a country where this resource is refined in Port Harcourt. For ten points, name this resource extracted in Nigeria by companies like Royal Dutch Shell.",
      "answer": "crude oil"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, a moral pressure known as “window guidance” prevented banks from making major lending pushes. A company based in this country introduced the “just in time” system to improve efficiency. This country’s prime minister suggested a “Three Arrows” approach to address its low inflation rate,decreasingproductivity,andagingworkingpopulation.“Abenomics”[ah-bay-nomics]wasundertaken in, for ten points, what country that experienced the “Lost Decade” after poor economic performance from companies such as Toyota and Sony?",
      "answer": "Japan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This character notes “that Nature might stand up / and say to all the world, ‘This was a man!’” while this man a fallen opponent. This character claims that “the evil that men do lives after them” after asking “Friends, Romans, countrymen, lend me your ears” as he comes to “bury” his fallen friend, “not to praise him.” For ten points, name this character from Shakespeare’s Julius Caesar who joins Octavius in fighting Cassius and Brutus after Caesar’s assassination.",
      "answer": [
        "Marc Antony",
        "Marcus Antonius",
        "in both answers,",
        "either name, and",
        "either underlined name"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A video taken at this event shows a Mi-8 helicopter colliding with a cable suspended from a crane, causing the helicopter to crash. The TORCH Report predicted tens of thousands of deaths due to the effects of this event. This was the first event to be classified as a INES level 7. The samosely illegally live in the “zone of alienation” near the site of this event; that exclusion zone includes the Red Forest and the city of Pripyat, which became a ghost town in this event’s aftermath. For ten points, name this 1986 meltdown of a Ukrainian nuclear power plant.",
      "answer": [
        "Chernobyl disaster",
        "additional information and synonyms of disaster"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While serving as this President’s Secretary of War, George Crawford was implicated in the Galphin Affair. This President’s Secretary of State negotiated an effort to build the Nicaragua Canal in the Clayton-Bulwer Treaty. Before becoming president, this man defeated Santa Anna at the Battle of Buena Vista during the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this President, nicknamed “Old Rough and Ready,” whose death after a year in office promoted Millard Fillmore to the presidency.",
      "answer": "Zachary Taylor"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Karl Goetz created a series of medals that depict this event with captions like “Business Above All” and “No Contraband.” The “coal dust” theory probably does not explain the second explosion that occurred during this event. This event may have been avoided had the zig-zag maneuver been carried out, and it was predicted by a newspaper which acknowledged a state of war between two nations. For ten points, name this event in which a British passenger ship was torpedoed by a German U-Boat, prompting the U.S. to enter World War I.",
        "answer": [
          "sinking of the RMS Lusitania",
          "equivalents"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Cabinet member questioned President Wilson’s sharp response, asking “why be so shocked by the drowning of a few people, if there is to be no objection to starving a nation?”, and resigned a month after the sinking.",
        "answer": "William Jennings Bryan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group was established with the Oath of Pontida. This group utilized the carroccio, which was defended by a group of knights known as the Company of Death. One emperor claimed power over members of this group at the Diet of Roncaglia, but that emperor, Frederick Barbarossa, was decisively defeated by this group at the Battle of Legnano. This group was rended obsolete after the end of the Hohenstaufen dynasty. For ten points, name this medieval alliance of Northern Italian city-states which opposed the influence of the Holy Roman Empire.",
        "answer": [
          "Lombard League",
          "Lega Lombarda"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the Battle of Legnano, Frederick Barbarossa quickly signed a peace named for what city, which was the original target of the League of Cambrai?",
        "answer": [
          "Venice",
          "Venezia",
          "Peace of Venice"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A ruler of this dynasty used “Hanging Judge” George Jeffreys to punish participants of a rebellion against him in the Bloody Assizes. A war with the Dutch during this dynasty’s reign included the devastating Raid on the Medway. An interregnum during this dynasty was dominated by elites known as the Grandees and included a government called the Protectorate. William and Mary’s Glorious Revolution overthrew a ruler from, for ten points, what dynasty that succeeded the Tudor Dynasty when James I ascended to the English throne?",
        "answer": "House of Stuart"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "For his supposed lack of good judgment, James I was termed the “wisest” one of what people “in Christendom” by Anthony Weldon?",
        "answer": "fool"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The incompetent George Percy took leadership of this colony after a gunpowder accident forced a leader to return to Europe. The Third Supply was to bolster this colony, but much of its supplies were left on Bermuda. Settlers first arrived at this location aboard the Discovery, Godspeed, and Susan Constant. The maxim “he who does not work shall not eat” governed this location, where John Rolfe grew tobacco. John Smith led, for ten points, what first permanent English settlement in Virginia?",
        "answer": "Jamestown"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This daughter of Powhatan allegedly saved the life of John Smith and married John Rolfe.",
        "answer": "Pocahontas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. Pedro Almodovar’s Glen Valley was announced as part of this event. As part of this event, the ownership of Wintris [vin-tris] by Sigmundur David was revealed during an interview with David, shortly before he stepped aside as Prime Minister. Mossack Fonseca was blamed for this event, whose source began in 2015 but became broadly public in April 2016 as the existence of 2.6 terabytes of data, involving over 10 million documents, was announced. For ten points, name this event in which the existence of hundreds of thousands of offshore companies was unintentionally revealed by a Central American firm.",
        "answer": "the leak of the Panama Papers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sigmundur David stepped aside as Prime Minister of this European country; Wintris was owed millions of dollars from numerous failed banks in this country.",
        "answer": "Iceland"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this work’s epilogue, a trio of ghosts including Queen Tye sing wordlessly. An offstage rendition of Psalm 104 follows a hymn in this opera that is to be sung in the audience’s native language. This opera is the final part of its composer’s Portrait trilogy. Its libretto, which is mostly taken from records of the Amarna period, depicts a king who sings the “Hymn to the Sun” and marries Nefertiti. For ten points, name this Philip Glass opera about a monotheistic pharaoh.",
        "answer": "Akhnaten"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This second entry in Glass’s Portrait Trilogy is loosely based on the early life of Mahatma Gandhi and is named for his philosophy of nonviolent resistance.",
        "answer": "Satyagraha"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author described a “sense of dissatisfaction” and the silent question “Is this all?” in the opening to one work. This co-founder of NARAL and author of The Second Stage described “the problem that has no name” as an inner voice saying “I want something more than my husband and my children and my home” in her most famous work. The National Organization for Women was first led by, for ten points, what American thinker, the author of The Feminine Mystique?",
        "answer": "Betty Friedan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Friedan supported this proposed Constitutional amendment, which would have guaranteed equality for women but was only ratified by 35, not 38, states during the 1970s.",
        "answer": "Equal Rights Amendment or ERA"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Robert Millikan was convinced that a paper about this phenomenon was incorrect and built “a machine shop in vacuo” to try to disprove it. A coil with a spark gap that sparked less when placed in a dark box led to the first observation of this phenomenon by Heinrich Hertz. Philipp Lenard found that this phenomenon did not depend on the intensity of light, but rather the frequency. In one of his Annus Mirabilis papers, Albert Einstein described this phenomenon, for which he won the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1921. For ten points, name this phenomenon in which electrons are emitted when light is shined upon metal.",
        "answer": "photoelectric effect"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In a more successful experiment, Millikan found what quantity using an electric field and tiny charged drops of oil?",
        "answer": [
          "fundamental electric charge",
          "charge of an electron",
          "elementary charge",
          "or e"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "3. GLADIATORS",
      "prompt": "In the wake of John F. Kennedy’s death, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Vice President who then took the Oath of Office.",
          "answer": "Lyndon Baines Johnson or LBJ"
        },
        {
          "question": "alleged assassin who was, two days later, shot by Jack Ruby.",
          "answer": "Lee Harvey Oswald"
        },
        {
          "question": "family member who iconically saluted the casket during the funeral procession.",
          "answer": [
            "John F. Kennedy, Jr. or JFK Jr.",
            "John John",
            "his son"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "national cemetery where Kennedy was buried.",
          "answer": "Arlington National Cemetery"
        },
        {
          "question": "sitting Supreme Court Chief Justice who spoke at the Capitol as Kennedy lie in state.",
          "answer": "Earl Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "sports league led by Pete Rozelle that did not postpone games.",
          "answer": "National Football League or NFL"
        },
        {
          "question": "African-American activist who called JFK’s murder “chickens coming home to roost”?",
          "answer": "Malcolm X"
        },
        {
          "question": "Baltimore-based naval hospital that performed Kennedy’s autopsy.",
          "answer": [
            "Bethesda Naval Hospital",
            "Walter Reed National Military Medical Center"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CAPTAIN COOK",
      "prompt": "In the career of Captain James Cook, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "country for which he sailed and served in the Royal Navy?",
          "answer": "Great Britain"
        },
        {
          "question": "continent he discovered on his first voyage that was later used as a penal colony?",
          "answer": "Australia"
        },
        {
          "question": "river he mapped joining Lake Ontario to the Atlantic Ocean?",
          "answer": "St. Lawrence River"
        },
        {
          "question": "island group, originally named the Sandwich Islands, where he was killed?",
          "answer": "Hawaiian Islands"
        },
        {
          "question": "inlet in Sydney he named for its variety of plant life?",
          "answer": "Botany Bay"
        },
        {
          "question": "ship he commanded during his first voyage?",
          "answer": "H.M.S. Endeavor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indonesian city formerly known as Batavia where that ship was repaired?",
          "answer": "Jakarta"
        },
        {
          "question": "man who was the first European in New Zealand until Cook’s trip there?",
          "answer": "Abel Tasman"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "GLADIATORS",
      "prompt": "Who or what in the history of gladiators was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Roman amphitheater in which they fought?",
          "answer": "Colosseum"
        },
        {
          "question": "gladiator who led a 73 BC uprising?",
          "answer": "Spartacus"
        },
        {
          "question": "main road of Rome where his army was crucified?",
          "answer": [
            "Appain Way",
            "Via Appia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "member of the First Triumvirate who ordered that crucifixion?",
          "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman Emperor that outlawed the games?",
          "answer": "Constantine I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor and son of Marcus Aurelius said to have performed as a bestiarius gladiator?",
          "answer": "Marcus Aurelius Commodus Antoninus Augustus"
        },
        {
          "question": "name of the “ad ludum” tattoos worn by gladiators?",
          "answer": "stigmata"
        },
        {
          "question": "southern Italian peoples played by many gladiators?",
          "answer": [
            "Samnites",
            "Samnians"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The initial invasion of this war may have sought to capture Jaber al-Sabah from Dasman Palace, but he fled and ruled in exile from a Saudi Arabian hotel room. In this war, the (20 pts)",
        "Republican Guard was defeated in a vast desert at the Battle of 73 Easting, called “the last great tank battle of the (10 pts)",
        "20th century.” Coalition forces in this war were led by “Stormin’” Norman Schwarzkopf, who devised this war’s tactical plan, Operation Desert Storm. For ten points, name this 1991 war in which the U.S. responded to Iraq’s invasion of Kuwait."
      ],
      "answer": "Persian Gulf War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was known as the “adolescent butcher” and gained an epithet after defeating Hiarbas. He married Aemilia Scaura after aiding her father against Gnaeus Papirius Carbo. This general forced the surrender of Tigranes the Great in a war against (20 pts)",
        "Mithridates VI. He helped Metellus Pius suppress Sertorius, and the Lex Gabinia gave him maritime powers to quash the Cilician pirates. After losing to a former ally at (10 pts)",
        "Pharsalus, he fled to Egypt, where Ptolemy XII ordered him dead. For ten points, name this member of the First Triumvirate with Crassus and Caesar."
      ],
      "answer": "Pompey the Great or Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was sentenced to death for his role in a prison break at Wadi el Natroun. He rose to his highest position when he beat Ahmed Shafik in an election. The National Salvation Front opposed this man, who (20 pts)",
        "awarded himself unlimited constitutional powers and was then replaced by the military with the transitional leader Adly Mansour. This leader of the (10 pts)",
        "Freedom and Justice Party was deposed in a 2013 coup by the current president Abdul al-Sisi. For ten points, name this member of the Muslim Brotherhood and successor of Hosni Mubarak as leader of Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Mohamed Morsi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man designated Pir Muhammad ibn Jahangir as his successor before allegedly dying of a fever brought on by drinking too much ice water. The Knights Hospitalier were massacrced in (20 pts)",
        "Smyrna on the orders of this man, who consolidated power at the Battle of the Terek River. This man used flaming camels to scare elephants during the siege of (10 pts)",
        "Delhi, and he defeated Bayezid the Thunderbolt at Ankara. This enemy of Toktamysh and the Golden Horde died while attempting to attack the Ming Dynasty. For ten points, name this lame conqueror who ruled from Samarkand."
      ],
      "answer": "Tamerlane"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man rose to his highest post after leading the ships Novara, Saida, and Helgoland in a raid on the Otranto Barrage. Following his overthrow, this man’s capital was taken in a one hundred day siege. This man first allied with the Axis over anger at the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Trianon, though his son was later kidnapped and wrapped into a carpet during Operation Panzerfaust, which was planned by Otto Skorzeny. (10 pts)",
        "Ferenc Szalai [fer-entz SA-lie] of the Arrow Cross Party took power after the overthrow of, for ten points, what admiral who led Hungary in World War II?"
      ],
      "answer": "Miklos Horthy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One side in this battle retreated to Bacoor Bay. Camara’s Flying Relief Column was sent to aid the losing side in this battle, which had originally wanted to fight at Subic Bay until the (20 pts)",
        "Castilla started leaking. The USS Olympia was the flagship of the victorious leader of this battle, who subsequently became the only “six star” admiral. The order “You (10 pts)",
        "may fire when ready Gridley” was given by the winning commander at, for ten points, what decisive victory for George Dewey in the Philippines during the Spanish-American War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Manila Bay"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In response to being called an Uncle Tom for her role in this film, one actress said “I’d rather make 700 dollars a week playing a maid, than seven dollars being one.” This film’s premiere was hosted by Mayor William Hartsfield, though local laws prevented (20 pts)",
        "Hattie McDaniel, who became the first African-American Oscar winner for her role in this film, from attending. Melanie Hamilton was played by Olivia de Havilland, one of the few (10 pts)",
        "surviving cast members from this film. The inflation-adjusted highest grossing film of all time is, for ten points, what 1939 film starring Vivien Leigh and Clark Gable as Scarlett O’Hara and Rhett Butler, which was based on a Margaret Mitchell novel?"
      ],
      "answer": "Gone With the Wind"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s overtures for peace talks were recorded in “The Vital Letters of [this man], Khrushchev, and Dulles.” He noted that colonization was justified with proper use of land in his “Ethics of War.” A manifesto named for this man and (20 pts)",
        "Albert Einstein became the founding charter of the Pugwash Conferences. His work “On Denoting” discusses definite and indefinite descriptions, and this author of (10 pts)",
        "“Why I Am Not a Christian” was an outspoken proponent of nuclear disarmament. For ten points, name this British philosopher who collaborated with Alfred, Lord Whitehead in Principia Mathematica."
      ],
      "answer": "Bertrand Russell"
    }
  ]
}